Hello! This episode of Bug Bounty Reports
Explained has the highest bounty of all my videos:
$3.4 million. The reason is it's a bug
in a blockchain network called Polygon
and it allowed stealing about $20 billion.
It was discovered by Leon Spacewalker.
Link to the original blogpost
is in the description. Enjoy!
This video is sponsored by Immunefi,
the leading bug bounty platform for Web3
with the world’s largest bounties. In the regular,
Web2 industry, we are used to most programs
having a maximum of 4-digit payouts or 5-digit at
best. On Immunefi, there are programs that pay
up to $10 mln dollars. It's life-changing money.
And web3 is an exciting technology. Personally, I've
already started learning it. If you to join me and
get ahead of everyone else, check out Immunefi.
Polygon is a network built on top of Ethereum.
It allows making more transactions with
cheaper fees than on Ethereum itself.
The main token of the Polygon network is called
MATIC and, interestingly, apart from being the
main token, it's also an MRC20 contract deployed
on the network. It allows transferring MATIC funds
without paying a fee. The network also allows
you to purchase an NFT. And let's imagine it's
2030 and BBRE Premium is sold as an NFT in the
Polygon network. You want to purchase it. You
have some cryptocurrency but in USDT coin which
is not on the Polygon network but is mapped to it.
Polygon allows us to swap your tokens for my
NFT. Of course, the naive way to do this is that
I could tell you to send me tokens first and then
you would hope that I would send you the NFT back.
And I'm honest, you can trust me but we discovered
smart contracts for a reason. It's to do
such transactions without having to trust the
other person. And the way we could do this
in Polygon network is as follows. First, we have
a Marketplace contract that's between me and you.
This contract will first generate an order of
you swapping your tokens for my NFT. It will also
assign an order ID. Then, the marketplace
will ask you to generate a signature
that you indeed want to swap your 500
USDT tokens for the BBRE Premium NFT.
The signature will contain the address of the
marketplace contract, the order id from step 2,
the expiration and, most importantly, how many
of what tokens you want to swap for what NFT.
And you sign all that with your private key.
And the marketplace will ask me to do the same
thing but instead I will swap my NFT for your
tokens. With these two signatures, the contract
will now carry out both transfers and make sure
that either both or none go through. And for this
the transferWithSig function is used. And pay
attention because this is the most important one
in the context of this bug. It takes
these parameters: the signature,
the amount to transfer, the data parameter
is only a hash that contains the order id,
amount and the token. It's not created
with a private key or anything like this.
It only prevents using this transferWithSig
function multiple times for the same order.
Then, there is the expiration in the form of a
block number and finally, the address to which
to send the funds. The function makes checks if
the amount is greater than zero, if the order
hasn't expired and if the same transfer isn't
being replayed. But notice it doesn't take the
address from which to carry out the transfer.
And this is a crucial information. So before
it finally calls the transferFrom function,
it has to recover the address of the sender.
ecrecover is the function that takes the signature
and data of the order to retrieve the address
of the wallet used to create the signature.
Actually, it's not ecrecover but ecrecovery
function that is used. It's only a wrapper
around ecrecover to make it more user-friendly.
And one of the first things it does is checking
if the signature is invalid. But if it is,
instead of throwing an error, the function
returns a 0x0 address. Now, in itself
it wouldn't be a problem. Until we take a look
at the _transfer function. There is only a check
if the transfer isn't done to the same contract
which is absolutely not a problem for us.
In the second line, it transfers funds from
the contract to the recipient. Of course,
_transfer and transferFrom functions are only
created to be used internally and you can't
just call them with whatever parameters. But
if you could force the ecrecovery function to
return a 0x0 address, you could transfer all the
funds from the contract to an arbitrary address.
How to do it? The first line of that function
checks if the signature is 65 characters.
So if you submit anything other than 65 characters
long, you are good to go. While all that swapping,
marketplaces may have sound complicated to
you, the proof of concept is ridiculously
simple. And to be honest, I don't even know if
the attacker really went through all these steps.
Maybe, he just noticed this function and
exploited it straight away. But personally,
I wanted to know how this transferWithSig function
is used in the real life. That's probably why it
took me twice more time than usual to create notes
for this video but I hope you appreciate that.
So transferWithSig is an external
function. You can call it without
making any marketplace transactions. Here is
the repository which you can clone. It creates
the fork of the network before the patch and
gives you the script to reproduce the attack.
Forking is also a way to test your smart contract
bugs before submitting vulnerability reports.
And this is how to call the transferWithSig
function. As the first argument, the signature,
use any buffer that's not 65 characters. As the
second, choose the amount you want to transfer.
Or, in other words, how much money you would like
to make. At the moment of the fix, December 5th,
the contract had over 9 billion MATIC
tokens. You could steal all of them.
The third argument is the hash of the data
but actually, the function only checks if the hash
wasn't used previously so you can use the hash of
almost anything. Expiration also doesn't matter
as long as it's a block number from the future.
And finally, the recipient address which
means where you want to transfer the money.
And with this single function call you could
steal all the money that were in the contract.
At the moment of the fix it was worth around,
$21 billion. And actually, before the fix was
deployed, over eight 800,000 MATIC tokens
were stolen which was worth around $2 mln.
The hunter who found the bug was rewarded
with $2.2 million of bounty which was above
the Polygon's maximum payout.
Even the hunter who duplicated
this report got the bounty of $1.2
million as an exception to the rule.
And as for the fix, the transferWithSig
function was removed. Lately I've been learning
smart contract security myself. So far, I only
document my learning journey but with time,
I will also start creating more content. If
you want to learn with me, subscribe to BBRE
Newsletter. The link is in the description.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!